<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The high court of justice. A sermon preached before the judge of assise at Leicester, Julie 30. 1652. / By Antonie Scattergood rectour of Winwick in North-hampton-shire.</title>
            <author>Scattergood, Antony, 1611-1687.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1652</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 67 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 38 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A94239</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S841</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1418_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R210320</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99869130</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99869130</idno>
            <idno type="VID">121493</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A94239)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 121493)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 255:E1418[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The high court of justice. A sermon preached before the judge of assise at Leicester, Julie 30. 1652. / By Antonie Scattergood rectour of Winwick in North-hampton-shire.</title>
                  <author>Scattergood, Antony, 1611-1687.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 73, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Roger Daniel,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>anno 1652.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Jan. 14."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>God --  Righteousness --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Justice --  Biblical teaching --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:121493:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE HIGH COURT OF JUSTICE.</p>
            <p>A SERMON Preached before the Judge of ASSISE at <hi>Leiceſter,</hi> Julie 30. 1652.</p>
            <p>By ANTONIE SCATTERGOOD <hi>Rectour</hi> of <hi>Winwick in North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hampton-ſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON. Printed by ROGER DANIEL Anno 1652.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:121493:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ORNATISSIMO VIRO D. THOMAE CAVE BARONETTO, ET LECTISSIMAE EJUS CONJUGI PENELOPAE HANC OPELLAM</p>
            <p>D. D. D.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>ANTONIUS SCATTERGOOD.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:121493:2"/>
            <head>THE HIGH COURT OF JUSTICE.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ROM. XIV. 10.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Wee ſhall all ſtand before the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment-ſeat of Chriſt.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Know it is uſuall in ſuch aſſemblies as this to han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle texts of Scripture pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to the preſent occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: Such as is Jethro's counſel to Moſes concerning the choice of Judges, <hi>Exod.</hi> 18.21. Moſes's charge to the Judges hee had cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, <hi>Deut.</hi> 1.16, 17. Samuels example, (that was a Judge itine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.15-17. in Bethel, and Gilgal, and Mizpeh, and Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mah) 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.3. King Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaphat's commiſſion to the Jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges hee ſet in the cities of Judah,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:121493:3"/>2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 19.6. Job's profeſſion of his own integrity, <hi>Job.</hi> 29.7-17. David's vow, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 101. thoſe Proverbs of Solomon, and paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the Prophets that either preſs the duties of Magiſtrates, or prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit Bribery, Cowardiſe, Partiality, or ſome other vice incident to that honourable calling. Such places as theſe are for the moſt part the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of Aſſiſe-ſermons: And indeed ſo worthy they are to bee ever freſh in the memories of all in autority, that I wiſh they were written on the walls of their houſes, or rather in the tables of their hearts. Yet my deſire beeing to ſpeak to all here preſent, and not to one onely, or a few (though thoſe few, yea that one, bee more conſiderable at this time then many others) I have therefore balked ſuch texts, &amp; cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen one of general &amp; perpetual con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment; a text that will not ſo
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:121493:3"/>much miniſter occaſion to the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher to ſatisſie the humour of thoſe that exſpect a Satyre from the pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit, and love to ſee the faults of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, great ones eſpecially, laſhed, while themſelves ſit untouched, as it will force us all, if well and duly weighed, to erect a tribunall every man in his own boſome, and to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Accuſers and Judges of our ſelves; a text that will not ſo much give occaſion the Preacher to tell the people what the Informer, and witneſs, and Pleader, and Jurer, and Judge ſhould do, as it will force us all, of what calling or rank ſoever, ſeriouſly to bethink ourſelves, and carefully to enquire of others, as they in the <hi>Acts, chapt.</hi> 2.37. and 9.6. and 16.30. What wee our<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſhould do. All here at Church have not buſineſs at the Court: The Sheriff's men will tell you ſo anon: Yea, many there are
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:121493:4"/>who never had, and haply never ſhall have, any quarrel or contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie to bee tried before an earthly Judge: But the Judge that <hi>cometh in the clouds every eie ſhall ſee him, Rev.</hi> 1.7. every one ſhall bee ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monned <hi>to appear before him, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive according to what hee hath done in the body, whether good or bad,</hi> 2 Cor. 5.10. <hi>Wee ſhal all ſtand before the judgement-ſeat of Chriſt.</hi> The text, yee ſee, is profitable at any time, for any congregation. And meethinketh it is alſo ſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble enough at this time, and ſutable enough to the preſent auditorie. Wee have a Judge, and an Aſſiſes in the Town; and wee have a Judge and an Aſſiſes in the Text: and each ought to reflect upon the other. The Trumpet, and Guard, and At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance, the Robes, the Tribunall, the Barre, the whole pomp and proceeding of Judges here below
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:121493:4"/>ſhould mind us of that awfull Judge who will one day <hi>deſcend from heaven with a ſhout, with the voice of the Archangel, and with the trump of God,</hi> 1 Theſſ. 4.16. <hi>and coming in the glorie of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, with his Angels and myriads of Saints,</hi> Mat. 16.27. Jude 14. ſhall erect his judgement-ſeat in the clouds, and there ſit upon the eternall life and death of all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind. Thus the affair in hand is an embleme of the Text: for an Aſſiſe is a little Dooms-day: And again the Text by Gods bleſſing may have great influence upon the affair in hand. For let all that have to do in matters apperteining to Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment but believe and remember theſe few words, <hi>Wee ſhall all ſtand before the judgement-ſeat of Chriſt,</hi> and I am conſident there will bee no malicious calumnies or falſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſations brought into the Court,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:121493:5"/>no rotten cauſe gilded over by bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed eloquence, no verdict given-in againſt evidence and Oath, no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting, no delaying of Juſtice, but all, from him that ſitteth on the Bench to the meaneſt Officer, will <hi>by the terrours of the Lord bee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded</hi> ſo to demean themſelves as to <hi>have alwayes a conſcience void of offenſe toward God &amp; toward men,</hi> Acts. 24.16. The Text then is a word ſpoken in fit ſeaſon; as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth further from our Saviours telling the High Prieſt and Councel of the Jews, when he was appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended and brought before them, that they ſhould ſee him come in the clouds of heaven, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.64. and from S. Pauls reaſoning be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Felix of the judgement to come, <hi>Acts.</hi> 24.25.</p>
            <p>My porch is big enough: It is time to walk into the Court. I have hitherto made way for my
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:121493:5"/>Text: Let us now make entrance into it. Therein three things are obvious to our view:
<list>
                  <item>1. A Judgement-ſeat;</item>
                  <item>2. The Perſon that ſhall ſit upon it;</item>
                  <item>3. The Perſons that ſhall ſtand before it. Whence three points of doctrine:
<list>
                        <item>1. <hi>There ſhal bee a Judgement;</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2. <hi>Christ ſhall bee the Judge;</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>3. <hi>The Judgement ſhall be ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">I. That there ſhal bee a Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment after death, though it bee an article of Chriſtian Faith, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty and privilege whereof is to look beyond the veil, and to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold things inviſible; yet was it not wholy hid from the ey of naturall Reaſon: for wee find the wiſer ſort of the Heathen making ſome diſcoveries of it. The Sibylls pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie of it. Plato and other Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:121493:6"/>prove it, in their diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes concerning the Immortality of the ſoul, and its condition after death. The Poets with their witty fanſies paint it out in their fables of Aeacus and his fellow-Judges, of the Elyſian fields, of Tityus's vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, of Tantalus's hunger &amp; thirſt, of the darkneſs and fire and furies of the infernall regions. If theſe by the glimmering light of Nature could ſee ſo much, how can wee wonder enough at thoſe Sadducees and Epicures amongſt us, that deny this truth now the Sun of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel ſhineth ſo bright about them? what can wee think, but that they are mere Atheiſts, and not worthy to bee diſputed with, ſince they deny our principles, and oppoſe both Scripture and Nature? Time will come when they ſhall feel what they will not now believe, and bewail their errour when it will bee
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:121493:6"/>too late. As for us, let us not bee deceived. Let not their evil words corrupt either our minds or our manners. Let not us follow ſwiniſh Epicures, who profeſs ourſelves Chriſts ſheep; but let us hear the voice of our Shepherd; &amp; while they deride the Scriptures, let us believe them. And they are as clear in this matter as any. Solomon ſaith to the voluptuous youngſter, <hi>Know thou that for all theſe things God will bring thee into judgement,</hi> Eccl. 11.9. and hee endeth that excellent book with that golden ſentence concerning the end of all things, <hi>God ſhall bring every work into judgement, with every ſecret thing whether it bee good or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it bee evil,</hi> Eccl. 12.14. Our Saviour in the Goſpel doth not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tell us that hee will come at the laſt day, and by his powerful voice raile up all unto judgement, <hi>Mat.</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:121493:7"/>16.27. <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.28, 29. <hi>and</hi> 6.39. but hee alſo punctually ſetteth down the ſignes of his coming, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24. and the maner of his proceeding, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25. And ſince the reſt of his words have proved faithfull and true, let us not make any queſtion of this. Hee foretold the particulars of his paſſion, the maner of his death, and the time of his reſurrection; Hee promiſſed to ſend the holy Ghoſt upon his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples; Hee threatned the ruine of the temple, the deſolation of Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, &amp; the rejection of the Jews. Let the accompliſhment of theſe predictions confirm our belief of the other. The ſame mouth ſpake all; and the ſame hand that hath ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled ſo many, will not fail in one. That this main point might be the more generally believed, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded his Apoſtles <hi>to teſtifie that it is hee that is ordained of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:121493:7"/>God to be the Judge of quick and dead,</hi> Acts 10.42. And accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly they almoſt in all their Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons and Epiſtles do teach and preſs it. It were tedious to cite all the places. S. Paul deſcribeth the maner of the Lords coming, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.15-17. And S. John amongſt his many other Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, had the white Throne, the rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the dead, the opening of the Books, the laſt judgement, and the execution of it revealed unto him, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.11-15. The like viſion had Daniel, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.9, 10, 13, 14. Yea, Enoch even in the beginning of the world was ſo cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of the end of it, that he ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth of the day of doom as if he had then ſeen it. And indeed he did ſee the day of Chriſts ſecond coming with the like eye to that wherewith Abraham beheld his firſt. See him as it were pointing
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:121493:8"/>with his finger at the Judge mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching in the clouds with all the company of heaven with him, Jude 14. <hi>Behold, the Lord cometh with ten thouſands of his Saints, to execute judgement upon all,</hi> &amp;c. This article of the later Judgement is not onely grounded (as yee ſee) upon the word, but we may draw arguments alſo to prove it from all the Attributes of God. His Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer will then be ſhewen in raiſing the dead out of the duſt, and bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all his rationall creatures before his Tribunall, and with one word of his mouth <hi>turning the wicked in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hell, and all the people that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat God.</hi> His Wiſdome will then appear, by <hi>bringing to light the hidden things of darkneſs</hi> and lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing open all the works and words and thoughts of men. His Truth will then be manifeſt, by perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the promiſes that he made to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:121493:8"/>his ſervants, and by executing the threats denounced againſt his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. Laſtly, his Juſtice and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy will then become unqueſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, which during the time of this life are much queſtioned. Here in this world God doth not alwaies reward men according to their works, but for the moſt part ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth his deareſt children to lie un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the croſs, while the wicked are laden with his benefits. Cain build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Cities, while Abel ſleepeth in the duſt; Eſau is a great Lord, while Jacob endureth an hard ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice; Chaſt Joſeph heth by the heels, while his wanton Miſtreſs is at liberty; Naboth's vineyard is uſurped by Ahab; Lazarus want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth relief at the gluttons door briefly. <hi>the rod of the ungodly lieth upon the back of the righteous;</hi> the devils goats tread down Gods he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritage: and all this while though
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:121493:9"/>God <hi>look upon them that deal trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherouſly, yet he holdeth his tongue when the wicked devoureth the man that is more righteous then he,</hi> Hab. 1.13. And becauſe God thundereth not as oft as men bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpheme, <hi>becauſe ſentence againſt their evil works is not executed ſpeedily, therefore the heart of the ſons of men is fully ſet in them to do evil,</hi> Eccleſ. 8.11. Nay, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God keepeth ſilence, they take his ſilence for conſent, and they <hi>think he is altogether ſuch an one as themſelves,</hi> Pſa. 50.21. Sure he loveth our perſons (ſay they) he owneth our cauſe, he is well pleaſed with our courſes, otherwiſe he would never pour his favours ſo plentifully on us. And thus they grow more hardened in their ſins. On the other ſide, the righteous comparing their own affliction with the proſperity of the wicked,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:121493:9"/>are ready to call into queſtion the juſtice of God, and the truth of his promiſes. This ſeeming confuſion that is in Gods dealings with men in this world, made not ſome mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Heathens alone to queſtion Providence (as we read Lucilius demanded of Seneca, <hi>Quid ita ſi providentia mundus agatur, tam multa bonis viris accidunt mala?</hi> but it moved the Prophet thus to expoſtulate with God himſelf, <hi>Righteous art thou, O Lord, when I plead with thee, yet let me talk with thee of thy judgements; Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doth the way of the wicked proſper? wherefore are all they happy that deal very treacherouſly? Jer.</hi> 12.1. Yea, this unevenneſs in the wayes of God made the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt ſtumble ſhrewdly, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.2, 3. <hi>As for me</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>my feet were almoſt gone, my ſteps had well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nigh ſlipt; For I was envious at
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:121493:10"/>the fooliſh, when I ſaw the proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the wicked.</hi> And ver. 13, 14. <hi>Verily I have cleanſed mine heart in vain, and waſhed mine hands in innocency; For all the day long have I been plagued, and chaſtened eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry morning.</hi> He began to think it a vam thing to ſerve God, if God rewarded his ſervants with no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter wages then afflictions. And ſurely Religion were the grandeſt folly in the world, and we Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans <hi>of all men the moſt miſerable,</hi> (as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh, 1 Cor. 15.19.) <hi>if in this life onely we had hope in Chriſt.</hi> If there were no recompenſe of reward to be looked for hereafter, who would <hi>chooſe to ſuffer affliction with the people of God, rather then to enjoy the pleaſures of ſin, and eſteem the reproch of Chriſt greater riches then the tredjures of a kingdome,</hi> as Moſes did, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 11.25, 26. The
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:121493:10"/>briny tears of repentance, and the bitter pills of mortification would never down with any of us, if not ſugred with after-hopes. But bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be God we are aſſured, that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all theſe gloomy dayes and doubtfull weather, the day of the revelation of the righteous judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God will appear, when thoſe Saints of his whom he had afflicted in this life ſhall be the more rewarded for their patience, and thoſe wicked wretches to whom he had been ſo bountifull, ſhall be the more ſharply puniſhed for the abuſe of his bleſſings. Yea, this very irregular proceeding of God now is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>a manifeſt token, of his righteous judgement</hi> hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as the Apoſtle ſaith, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.5. The Wiſe man argueth in like manner, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 3.16, 17. For obſerving the cruelty and injuſtice of men in great place and authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:121493:11"/>how in ſtead of being a ſhelter and ſanctuary to the oppreſſed, they proved unto them <hi>a briar and a thorn-hedge,</hi> in ſtead of being pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trones of laws they perverted them, making uſe of their power to do miſchief, and turning their Courts of Juſtice into dens of rapine, into meer butcheries and ſhops of cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty, what inferreth he hence? Not what they Ezek. 9.9. <hi>The Lord hath forſaken the earth, and the Lord ſeeth not;</hi> but what his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth in the like caſe, Pſal. 12.5. <hi>For the oppreſſion of the poor, for the ſighing of the needy the Lord will ariſe,</hi> &amp;c. Solomon from the cruell and unjuſt courſes of Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates inferreth the juſt judgement of God, and how there ſhall be a time when he <hi>that is higher then the higheſt</hi> will call them to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count for all <hi>their oppreſsion of the poor, and their violent perverting
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:121493:11"/>judgement and juſtiee.</hi> For thus he ſaith, <hi>Moreover, I ſaw under the ſun the place of judgement, that wickedneſs was there; and the place of righteouſneſs, that iniquity was there. I ſaid in mine heart, God ſhall judge the righteous and the wicked; for there is a time there for every purpoſe and for every work.</hi> Thus Solomon, like Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, found honey in the carcaſes e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of lions. And thus may the children of God do ſtill. The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperous wickedneſs of profane per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, which emboldeneth them in their waies of cruelty and tyrannie, and maketh them <hi>ſay in their hearts, God hath forgotten, he hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth his face, he will never ſee it,</hi> Pſal. 10.11. even that very ſame thing, though it oft wring tears from the eyes of the godly, yet it affordeth them a towell to wipe their cheeks withall, it being a
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:121493:12"/>ſtrong argument to aſſure their hearts, that <hi>a time of refreſhing will come from the preſence of the Lord, Acts</hi> 3.19. when there ſhall be no more place left for thoſe ſilly objections againſt Divine Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, Why is this villain proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous? and why that Saint in mife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry? <hi>Cur ſceleris pretium ille cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem tulit, hic diadema?</hi> Why was that traitour dreſſed with an hemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en halter, and this with a gold chain or a diadem? Then the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.5. the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the exact juſtice of God will be ſo evident, that even his enemies ſhall be forced to ſay, <hi>Verily there is a reward for the righteous, doubtleſs there is a God that judgeth the earth,</hi> Pſal. 58, 11, A day of judgement then ſhall come.</p>
            <p>But when?</p>
            <p>Some profane ones ask the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:121493:12"/>2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. ſcoffing at Gods ſlackneſs, and thinking, becauſe it is not yet, that it will be never. But <hi>the Lord is not ſlack as they count ſlackneſs.</hi> He doth but ſtay till his harveſt be ripe; then he will ſend forth his reapers, <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.30. he tarrieth but till his elect be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed, and then <hi>he that ſhall come, will come, and will not tarry,</hi> Hebr. 10.37.</p>
            <p>Others too curious have taken on them to calculate the period of the world, both Gentiles, Jews, and Chriſtians. Plato and Pytha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goras, among the Heathens, ſaid all this elementary frame ſhall be diſſolved after ſix and thirty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand yeers. Elias a Jew, but not the Tiſhbite, but a cabaliſticall Rabbine of a far meaner ſtamp, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth the world but a ſixth part of that term which thoſe Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers do, and ſaith it ſhall endure
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:121493:13"/>but ſix thouſand yeers; which he equally parcelleth out thus, two thouſand before the Law, two thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand under, two thouſand after. But he groſly erreth in the two firſt particulars; for from the creation of the world to the giving of the Law were above five hundred years more then his accompt, and from the Law to Chriſt almoſt five hundred years leſs. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we may well ſuſpect him in the laſt particular, which was the furtheſt off from his ken. But his totall ſumme of ſix thouſand years paſſed for currant with many of the antient Fathers, whileſt they compared Gods creating the world in ſix dayes with that place of S. Peter, <hi>One day is with the Lord as a thouſand years, and a thouſand years as one day,</hi> 2 Pet. 3.8. It would bee endleſs, and indeed it is needleſs, to acquaint you with the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:121493:13"/>ſeverall opinions of Chriſtian wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters concerning the time of Chriſt's ſecond coming; there having been ſome almoſt in every age that have ventured to ſet the year, if not the day, of theſe grand Aſſiſes: Moſt of which conjectures Time the mother of Truth hath already con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced to bee as falſe as they were bold; and ſo without doubt it will confute the reſt. For none know nor can know the end of the world but hee that began it. <hi>Times and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are in the Fathers power,</hi> Acts 1.7. this eſpecially; <hi>Mark</hi> 13.32. <hi>Of that day and that hour knoweth no man, no not the angels which are in heaven, neither the Son, but the Father:</hi> Not the Son, that is, not as man, or not at that time, (for his knowledge was gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duall, <hi>Luke</hi> 2.52. and mixed with ſome ignorance, <hi>Mark</hi> 11.13.) or not as Mediatour, ſo as to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:121493:14"/>reveal it to his Church: Thus the Son knew not the day of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. From 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.2. <hi>The day of the Lord ſo cometh as a thief in the night,</hi> ſome conclude, but very weakly, that Chriſt ſhall come in the night. The uncertainty of this appeareth from <hi>Mark</hi> 13.35. <hi>Yee know not when the Master of the houſe cometh, at even, or at midnight, orat the cock-crowing, or in the morning.</hi> Beſides, it is called <hi>the day of the Lord,</hi> 1 Cor. 5.5. 2 Cor. 1.14. 2 Pet. 3.10. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, when it is night with us, it is day in the other hemiſphere. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther night or day, how near it is wee may not affirm, yet that it is not far off wee may gather from thoſe prognoſticks that our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour hath given us, moſt whereof are come to paſſe already; as the ariſing of falſe Chriſts and falſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, perſecuting of true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:121493:14"/>wars and rumours of wars, peſtilences and famines, quakings of the earth, and ſearfull ſignes in heaven, iniquity everywhere aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and charity everywhere aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. Theſe buds plainly tell us that the Sun of righteouſneſs draweth nigh. Let us therefore lift up our heads, and gird up our loins, that hee may not come upon us and paſs by us before wee bee aware. Let the ſound of the Archangels trumpet bee ever in our ears, as S. Hierome ſaith it was in his: Let the fear and remembrance of that dreadfull tribunall bee continually in our minds. But how far ſoever the generall Judgement bee off, this let us know, that our particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar judgement is at hand: For this immediately followeth our death. So ſaith the Apoſtle, Heb. 9.27. <hi>It is appointed unto men once to die, but after this the judgement.</hi> No
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:121493:15"/>ſooner ſhal thy ſoul leave her earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tabernacle, but ſhee ſhall ſtand before her Judge, who having paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed an unalterable doom upon her, ſhee ſhall enter into endleſs joyes or pains. This ſhal bee as the Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-ſeſſions; that other like the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Aſſiſes. Thou ſhalt know by this how it will go with thee then. Well, Beloved, this alſo is unknown to us. Though wee cannot all ſay as Iſaac, Gen. 27. that <hi>wee are old;</hi> yet wee may all ſay as hee did, <hi>Wee know not the day of our death.</hi> Let this conſideration therefore preſs the ſame duty of Watchfulneſs. <hi>Ideo latet unus dies ut obſerventur omnes:</hi> God hath on purpoſe kept the knowledge of this one day from us, that hee might have our ſervice every day; that wee ſhould never bee ſecure, but ever ready, ever do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our Maſters buſineſs, ever caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up our own accompts, ever con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering our later end; like wiſe
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:121493:15"/>virgins, ever trimming our lamps; like faithfull ſervants, ever employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and improving our talents; that ſo when our Maſter cometh, and findeth us about his work, wee may receive his wages, or rather his gift, eternall life. So much of the firſt point, That there ſhal bee a Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Come we now to the ſecond,</p>
            <p n="2">II. <hi>Christ ſhall bee the Judge.</hi> To bee a Judge here upon earth (though the Manichees and Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts of old did, and the Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts their ſucceſſours now do cry it down) is an high and honourable calling. To bee an oracle of juſtice, a refuge for wronged innocencie, a mainteiner of Truth and Peace, a prop and pillar of the State; <hi>To give eyes to the blind, and feet to the lame; To break the jaws of op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſours, and pluck the ſpoil out of their teeth,</hi> Job 29.15, 17. To drive away wickedneſs and wicked
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:121493:16"/>men with a caſt of his ey or with the breath of his mouth, <hi>Pro.</hi> 20.8, 26. To carry the life &amp; livelihood of others on the tip of his tongue; Such actions as theſe, ſo great, ſo good, lift a man almoſt above hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity. And indeed as Judges do Gods work, (<hi>The judgement is Gods,</hi> Deut. 1.17. and, <hi>Yee judge not for man, but for the Lord,</hi> 2 Chron. 19.6.) ſo God giveth Judges his own title, Pſal. 82.6. <hi>I have ſaid, Yee are Gods, and all of you are children of the moſt High.</hi> If theſe that ride circuits here below, and exſecute judgement and juſtice but in ſome ſmall province, have ſo great honour and dignity laid upon them, how unconceiva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble will the autority and majeſty of that Perſon bee that ſhall bee Lord Chief Juſtice of heaven and earth, that ſhall bring in his hand the keyes of Hell and Death, and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:121493:16"/>ſhall cauſe a generall Gaol-deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very to bee made, that ſhall exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe Commiſſion of <hi>Oyer &amp; Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miner</hi> over all both men and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, and ſhall paſs an unrepeala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſentence upon both! And to this height is Chriſt advanced. <hi>All power is given him in heaven and in earth,</hi> Matth. 28.18. Hee is made not onely <hi>Head of his Church</hi> Epheſ. 5.23. but <hi>Lord and Judge of all,</hi> Acts 10.36, 42. <hi>All things are put under his feet; and hee is ſet far above all principality and power, and might and dominion, and every name that is named not onely in this world, but alſo in that which is to come,</hi> Epheſ. 1.20.22.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> But doth not Chriſt ſay, <hi>If any man hear my words, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve not, I judge him not: for I came not to judge the world, but to ſave the world,</hi> John 12.47? And the like wee have John 3.17.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:121493:17"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> Such places are to bee un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of that coming which is paſt, not of that which is to come. Chriſt came not indeed to judge the world, but hee ſhall come to judge it. Hee came in poverty, but hee ſhall come in power; Hee came in the form of a ſervant, and in the ſimilitude of ſinfull fleſh; but hee ſhall come in the glorie of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: Hee came to bee judged, but hee ſhall come to judge even thoſe that judged him: Hee came like a Lamb, to bee ſacrificed for ſin; but hee ſhall come like a Lion, to tear all impenitent and unbelieying ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners in pieces. At his firſt coming ſuch was his meekneſs and humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, that hee hid himſelf that hee might not bee a King, <hi>John</hi> 6.15. but ſuch ſhall bee the ſplendour and terrour of his ſecond coming, that even Kings and Potentates ſhall ſeek to hide themſelves from
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:121493:17"/>his preſence, <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.15-17. When hee was upon earth, hee refuſed to bee a Judge of civile matters and a divider of earthly inheritances; <hi>Man, who made mee a Judge or a divider over you?</hi> Luke 12.14. but when hee cometh in the clouds of heaven, hee will bee a Judge and a divider indeed: hee will beſtow the manſions of glorie on the veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of grace, and, like his type Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhua, divide the heavenly Canaan among all the Iſrael of God, giving to one autority over five cities, to another over ten, <hi>Luke</hi> 19.17, 19.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> But how and why is Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment attributed to Chriſt, ſince <hi>God is Judge of all the earth,</hi> Gen. 18.25. Yea, ſince <hi>God is Judge himſelf,</hi> Pſal. 50.6?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> How and why! Let the Arian and Socinian hear how and why. Chriſt is therefore <hi>Judge of all,</hi> Heb. 12.23. becauſe hee is
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:121493:18"/>
               <hi>God over all,</hi> Rom. 9.5. His Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity and his Autority inferre each other. That which in the Text the Apoſtle calleth <hi>ſtanding before the judgement-ſeat of Chriſt,</hi> in the twelfth verſe hee calleth <hi>Giving ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count to God; So then,</hi> ſaith hee, <hi>every one of us ſhall give account of himſelf to God.</hi> So then Chriſt is God. And indeed the Father com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municateth both his nature and his power unto him. <hi>Hee hath given all things into his hand,</hi> Joh. 3.35. and <hi>hee hath given him autority to exſecute judgement becauſe hee is the Son of man,</hi> Joh. 5.27. But wee muſt not imagin that by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſting the Son with this power the Father hath deveſted himſelf of it: For hee ſtill reteineth the power hee hath given. As in reſpect of eſſence, the Son is in the Father, and the Father in the Son; ſo in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of action, the Son worketh
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:121493:18"/>from the Father, and the Father by the Son, <hi>John</hi> 17.21-23. Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the particular in hand; That of our Saviour, <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.22. <hi>The Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther judgeth no man, but hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted all judgement to the Son,</hi> is excellently expounded by S. Paul, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.31. <hi>God hath appointed a day in the which hee will judge the world in righteouſneſs by that man whom hee hath ordained.</hi> Yet ſhall not Chriſt ſit as a delegate or ſubordinate Judge, but as a Judge Paramount, principall and abſolute, from whom there ſhall bee no ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal, whoſe ſentence ſhall not bee traverſed, nor his power reſiſted. For hee ſhall judge not as Man onely, nor as God onely, but as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as both together. As Man, hee ſhall come in the clouds of heaven, and ſit on the tribunall; as God, hee ſhall raiſe the dead, and force all to ſtand before him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:121493:19"/>As Man, every ey ſhall behold him; as God, hee ſhall behold every thought, and diſcover every deed of darkneſs: As Man, hee ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce the ſentence; as God, hee ſhall fulfill and exſecute it. The Scripture aſſcribeth the laſt Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to three ſorts of Judges; to God, to Chriſt, to the Saints. God, even the whole Trinity, ſhall bee the Judge, in reſpect of judiciarie power: Chriſt ſhall bee the Judge, in reſpect of his viſible appearance and audible promulgation of the ſentence: <hi>The Saints ſhall judge the world,</hi> 1 Cor. 6.2. in reſpect of conſent and approbation. God ſhal judge, as the <hi>King who is ſupreme;</hi> Chriſt ſhall judge, <hi>as a Judge ſent by him for the puniſhment of evil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doers &amp; for the praiſe of them that do well,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.13, 14. The Saints ſhall judge, as the honeſt Juſtices, and Gentlemen and body
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:121493:19"/>of the County, who <hi>when their ears hear an upright Judge, then they bleſs him; and when their eyes ſee him, they give witneſs to him,</hi> Job 29.11.</p>
            <p n="1">I. If Chriſt bee Judge, <hi>then the judgement ſhall bee according to truth,</hi> Rom. 2.2. <hi>The Judge of all the earth will do right,</hi> Gen. 18.25. Judges of but part of the earth oft erre in judgement. <hi>Great men are not alwayes wiſe, neither do the aged alwayes underſtand judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> ſaith Elihu, Job 32.9. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times Judges would find out the truth, but cannot: ſometimes they can find it out, but will not; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times they do find it out, but are driven from it. Truth lieth (as the Philoſopher ſaid) in a pit; and ſome Judges have not wherewith to draw it out. It is ſometimes ſo covered with darkneſs, and the way to it ſo intricate &amp; perplexed, &amp; Falſhood
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:121493:20"/>now and then meeteth the Judge in ſo handſome a diſguiſe, that it is no wonder to ſee even a good man miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken, to ſee an Iſaac think well of an Eſau, <hi>Gen.</hi> 25.28. a Samuel of an Eliab, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.6. a whole college of Apoſtles of a Judas, <hi>Mat</hi> 26.22. <hi>Joh.</hi> 13.21-26. But er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour in judgement ariſeth oftner from want of will to do right then from want of skill, the Judge ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther not having the patience to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford the cauſe a full hearing and to examin and ſift matters to the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome, or elſe having his eyes blear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with paſſion, or blinded with gifts. And it not ſeldome happen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that though the Judge find out the truth, and could find in his heart to maintein it, yet hee is dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven from it; either ſome great mans frown or letter being a Prohibition to him; and then</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Contra libertum Caeſaris ire ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met,</hi>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:121493:20"/>hee is afraid not to ſeem Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſars friend, <hi>John</hi> 19.12, 13. or hee is afraid to anger the beaſt with many heads, the multitude; &amp; then Barabbas is releaſed, and Chriſt is condemned by Pilate, <hi>Mark</hi> 15.15. <hi>Luke</hi> 23.23, and Paul by Felix is left bound, <hi>Acts</hi> 24.27. Laſtly, it is a thing too often ſeen, that after the Judge hath worthily done his part, and juſtly doomed a malefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour to death, ſome greater power interveneth and reſcueth him from the gallows, granting him either a Pardon or a Reprive. Hence it fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently happeneth, what the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet complaineth of, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59.14. that <hi>judgement is turned away back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, &amp; juſtice ſtandeth afarre off,</hi> that <hi>truth falleth in the ſtreet, and equity cannot enter;</hi> that thoſe old ſcenes are in every age oft acted over, that Joſeph is condemned as a vitious perſon, that Mephibo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth's
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:121493:21"/>eſtate is beſtowed upon a ſycophant, that Naboth fareth the worſe for having a good vineyard, and Micaiah loſeth his liberty for not empriſoning the truth; that, as Cyprian ſaith, <hi>inter leges ipſas de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquitur,</hi> that JUS is turned into VIS, Right overturned by Might. Certain it is, that while darkneſs is in the minds of men, and the Prince of darkneſs is ſuffered to tempt, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt other Vanities that are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Sun, that will ſtill bee one that yee heard Solomon complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Eccl.</hi> 3.16. that <hi>in the place of judgement wickedneſs is there, &amp; in the place of righteouſneſs iniquity is there.</hi> Under the Sun it will bee ſo: But when the Sun in the firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhal bee put out, then the Sun of righteouſneſs will ſhine forth, then a <hi>Judge will ſit in the throne that will judge right,</hi> Pſal. 9.4. and <hi>there ſhall bee no unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:121493:21"/>in him,</hi> Pſal. 92.15. For hee hath all the properties of a complete Judge, Wiſdome, Power, Juſtice, all infinite.</p>
            <p>Firſt, his Wiſdome is ſuch, that his eyes cannot bee blinded. <hi>The darkneſs is no darkneſs to him,</hi> Pſal. 139. Hee prieth into the cloſeſt corners, even into thoſe of the heart. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is his peculiar title, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.24. <hi>All things are</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ſtipped naked, ripped open before him,</hi> Heb. 4.13. Thoſe that have gone in the dark, and ſought deep to hide their counſel from the Lord, ſhall at the day of judgement find their cunning con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivances to have been to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. All cloſe plots, all ſecret cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berings, all curtain-ſins ſhall then bee brought to light; all hypocriſy ſhall bee unveiled, and every mask pulled off. Even in the dayes of his fleſh Chriſt <hi>knew what was in man,</hi>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:121493:22"/>John 2.25. hee knew Nathanael to bee a true Iſraelite, <hi>John</hi> 1.47. and Judas to bee a devil, <hi>John</hi> 6.70. how much more then in the day of his glorie ſhall hee <hi>bring to light the hidden things of darkneſs, and make manifeſt the counſels of the hearts?</hi> 1 Cor. 4.5. The wicked ſhall at that day call to the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains and rocks to cover them, <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.16. but in vain. For impoſſible it will bee for thee to bee hid. For beſides the omniſcience of the Judge a whole cloud of witneſſes wil ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear againſt thee. I. Every ſin thou haſt committed, if thou ſuffer it to lie down in the duſt with thee, will bee ſure to riſe up in judgement againſt thee. Many ſins are ſaid to cry now, as Murder, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.10. Uncleanneſs, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.20. Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.7. Keeping-back the labourers hire, <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.4. but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very ſin will have a voice at that
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:121493:22"/>day to cry for vengeance, if its mouth bee not ſtopped in the mean time with that bloud which ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth better things, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12.24. II. Every creature which thou haſt abuled will put up a bill of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictment. The lands or livings that by fraud or violence thou haſt u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurped, and deteineſt from the right owners, even theſe <hi>will cry againſt thee, and the furrows thereof will complain,</hi> Job 31.38. If <hi>thou buildeſt thy houſe by unrighteouſneſs, and thy chambers by wrong, wo unto thee,</hi> Jer. 22.13. <hi>for the ſtone ſhall cry out of the wall, and the beam out of the timber ſhall anſwer it,</hi> Hab. 2.11. The gold and ſilver that thou haſt either ill got, or ill kept, or ill ſpent, will prove an ill treaſure, even a treaſure of wrath, at the laſt day, <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.3, 4. III. Satan, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>that adverſarie in judgement,</hi> as S. Peter calleth him, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.8.
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:121493:23"/>who hath all thy life-time been <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>a Tempter,</hi> will at the day of judgement eſpecially make good his name <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and play the <hi>Devil</hi> indeed, accuſing thee of thoſe ſins to which he tempted thee. IV. But if all elſe ſhould bee ſilent, thou haſt that in thy boſome that will ſpeak loud enough, a book wherein all thy works, &amp; words, &amp; thoughts are written. This though now perhaps ſeldome looked into, but cloſed and faſt ſealed, ſhall then bee ſpread wide open, &amp; bee as bad as a thouſand witneſſes againſt thee, It wil bee a teſtimonie beyond all exception: for it was written all with thine own hand, &amp; kept alway in thine own cabinet. This is one of thoſe books mentioned <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.12. even the book of thy Conſcience, which ſhall <hi>bear witneſs, and either accuſe or excuſe</hi> thee before thy Judge, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.16. But indeed
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:121493:23"/>the Judge ſhall need no proof or evidence, for hee knoweth all things of himſelf, and <hi>needeth not that any ſhould teſtifie of man,</hi> John 2.25. In the vaſt volume of his Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience <hi>all our membres were writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten before they were faſhioned.</hi> Hee is not onely <hi>acquainted with all our wayes,</hi> but <hi>there is not a word in our tongue that hee knoweth not altogether:</hi> yea, <hi>hee underſtandeth our thoughts afarre off,</hi> as the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt moſt excellently, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139. As hee <hi>putteth tears into a bottle,</hi> Pſal. 58.8. ſo hee <hi>ſoweth and ſeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth up tranſgreſſions in a bag,</hi> Job 14.17. Hee now <hi>ſetteth thine ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities before him, even thy ſecret ſins in the light of his countenance,</hi> Pſal. 90.8. and time will come (though thou thinkeſt otherwiſe) <hi>when hee will ſet all in order before thine eyes,</hi> Pſal. 50.21.</p>
            <p>Secondly, as in reſpect of his
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:121493:24"/>Wiſdome the Judge may be ſaid to be <hi>Totus oculus,</hi> ſo in reſpect of his power hee may bee ſaid to bee <hi>Totus manus.</hi> Other Judges are oft hindred (as I ſaid) in the exſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of Juſtice: But there will bee no ſtanding againſt this Judge, no appealing from him. Hee is <hi>high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er then the higheſt,</hi> Eccl. 5.8. <hi>And his Kingdome ruleth over all,</hi> Pſal. 103.19. His hand will bee found no ſhorter at the laſt day then it was at the firſt; but as at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the world ſo at the end his Word will bee his Work. <hi>He ſpake the word and we were made</hi> at firſt: <hi>Pſ.</hi> 33.9. &amp; when hee ſaith, <hi>Return yee children of men,</hi> Pſal. 90.3. wee ſhall be made anew. With his word hee drew us all out of that old <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>os</hi> (if I may ſo ſpeak) and placed us here on earth; and with his word hee will people both heaven and hell, and fix that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:121493:24"/>
               <hi>great gulf,</hi> Luke 16.26. betwixt them.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, his Juſtice is of equall dimenſions with his Wiſdome and Power. And indeed where this is wanting in a Judge, the other two ſerve but to arm Iniquity, and to make it ſo much the more miſchie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous. But this great Judge is good as well as great. Hee is Juſtice it ſelf; the true Melchiſedech, <hi>the King of righteouſneſs.</hi> His name is, THE LORD OUR RIGHTEOUS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NESS, <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.6. and his nature is, <hi>to love righteouſneſs, and to hate wickedneſs,</hi> Pſal. 45.7. <hi>Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſhall go before him,</hi> Pſal. 85.13. Righteouſneſs ſhall bee under him: <hi>Righteouſneſs &amp; judgement are the habitation of his throne.</hi> Pſal. 97.2. Righteouſneſs ſhall bee round about him: <hi>Righteouſneſs ſhall bee the girdle of his loins, and faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs the girdle of his reins,</hi> Iſa. 11.7.
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:121493:25"/>So righteous hee was here upon earth, that none of his enemies could convince him of ſin, <hi>John</hi> 8.46, Neither Herode nor Pilate could find any fault in him, <hi>Luke</hi> 23.14, 15. Yea, the very devil cried out, <hi>Mark</hi> 1.24. <hi>I know thee who thou art, the Holy one of God.</hi> But though this Judge were ever <hi>righteous in all his wayes, and holy in all his works,</hi> Pſal. 145.17. yet then eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially will his righteouſneſs appear, <hi>when hee cometh, when hee cometh to judge the earth, when hee ſhall judge the world with righteouſneſs, and the people with his truth,</hi> Pſal. 96.13. His judgements now though ever juſt yet are often ſecret, his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours and his puniſhments beeing ſo promiſcuouſly dealt, and all things coming ſo alike to all, that there is no judging of love or ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred by outward events, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 9.1, 2. But at the laſt day his judgement
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:121493:25"/>will bee manifeſt as well as juſt. Now hee loveth to ſit upon his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie-ſeat and his throne of grace, to encline his ear to prayers, to bee mollified with tears, to bee ſwayed with ſighs, to receive ſuits, and to grant Reprives and Pardons: But at the day of Judgement his Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and Long-ſuffering will bee at an end: Then no entreaties, no tears, no promiſſes, no friends, no media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhall further prevail with him; <hi>but putting-on righteouſneſs as a breastplate, and an helmet of ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon his head, and putting-on the garments of vengeance for cloth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and beeing clad with zele as a cloak, according to their deeds ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly hee will repay furie to his adverſaries and recompenſe to his enemies,</hi> Iſa. 59.17, 18.</p>
            <p n="2">II. If Chriſt ſhall bee the Judge, oh how ſhall Pilate tremble that condemned him, and Judas that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:121493:26"/>him, and the Jews that thirſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for his bloud, and all that any wayes were conſenting to his death! And that (let mee tell you) many thouſands are that think themſelves far enough from ſuch horrid impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. They that now deſpiſe his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, reject the offers of grace, diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey the Goſpel, profane the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, count the Croſs fooliſhneſs, &amp; will not relie on a crucified Saviour, ſuch, how well ſoever conceited of themſelves, allow the fact of the Jews in crucifying of Chriſt; and, had they lived in that place and at that time, they would have had an hand in that bloud which they now <hi>trample under foot and account as a commonthing,</hi> Hebr. 10.29. Yea, they do even now in ſome ſort <hi>cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifie the Son of God afreſh, and put him to open ſhame,</hi> &amp; pierce him again &amp; again with their ſinnes, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.6. When ſuch as theſe ſhall <hi>behold him
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:121493:26"/>whom they have pierced,</hi> how ſhall their <hi>faces gather blackneſs, rotten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs enter into their bones,</hi> and their hearts bee overwhelmed with fear and aſtoniſhment! They were here offended at Chriſts humility: they ſhall bee much more offended at his glorie: They were here aſhamed of him: then hee will bee aſhamed of them: They would not hear his gentle &amp; mild voice to their conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; they ſhall therefore hear his terrible and dreadfull voice to their confuſion: They would not come to him for eaſe and refreſhment, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.29. they ſhall therefore depart from him into everlaſting fire, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.41. If in the ſtate of his humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation hee was able with a word to throw his apprehenders on their backs, <hi>Joh.</hi> 18.6. how caſily then, when hee <hi>ariſeth to judgement, ſhall his enemies</hi> (that would not appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend him by faith) <hi>bee ſcattered,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:121493:27"/>and they that hate him, flee before him!</hi> Pſal. 68.1. Now <hi>conſider this, yee that forget God, leſt hee then tear you in pieces, &amp; there bee none to deliver,</hi> Pſal. 50.22. Knowing the terrour of the Lord, let us bee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to look about us while wee have time &amp; place, before <hi>that great and notable day of the Lord come,</hi> Acts 2.20. That will bee the Lords day, a day of glorie: In this our day, the day of grace, <hi>while it is called To day,</hi> let us hearken to his voice, <hi>and conſider the things that belong to our peace, leſt hereafter they bee hid from our eyes,</hi> Luke 19.41. Let us now curb our luſts, &amp; break off our ſinful courſes, &amp; <hi>live in all holy converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion &amp; godlineſs,</hi> 2 Pet. 3.11. <hi>Let us kiſs the Son, leſt he bee angry, &amp; wee periſh when his wrath is kindled:</hi> Then <hi>bleſſed are they</hi> and onely they <hi>that put their truſt in him,</hi> Pſal. 2.12. I am fallen on a third Uſe.</p>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:121493:27"/>
            <p n="3">III. If Chriſt be Judge, then lift up your heads, &amp; comfort your hearts, all true Chriſtians. Though <hi>his eyes bee as a flame of fire, &amp; his voice as the ſound of many waters,</hi> Rev. 1.14, 15. though <hi>a fiery ſtream iſſue &amp; come forth from before him,</hi> Dan. 7.10. though at his coming <hi>the heavens ſhall paſs away with a great noiſe, &amp; the elements ſhall melt with fervent heat, &amp; the earth &amp; the works that are therein ſhall bee burnt up.</hi> 2 Pet. 3.10. though <hi>as wax melteth before the fire, the wicked periſh at the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Judge, yet let the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous bee glad, let them rejoyce yea let them exceedingly rejoice,</hi> Pſal. 68.2, 3. That great flame, that ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour all things elſe, ſhall not touch them. Let them not fear any thing, neither Sin, nor Satan, nor Hell. They have a Friend in the Court, <hi>that is able to ſave them to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt,</hi> Heb. 7.25. The Judge him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:121493:28"/>that ſitteth on the bench will bee their Advocate, &amp; plead their cauſe. Hee is their <hi>Brother,</hi> Heb. 2.11. their <hi>Husband,</hi> 2 Cor. 11.2. their <hi>Head,</hi> Col. 1.18. their <hi>Redeemer,</hi> Rev. 5.9. Hee ſhed his bloud for them on the Croſs; ſhall he not then ſpeak a word for them on the tribunall? Hee ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared at his firſt coming like us, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king not onely our infirmities but our iniquities upon him, that at his ſecond coming wee might bee <hi>like him,</hi> and <hi>appear with him in glorie,</hi> Col. 3.4. 1 Joh. 3.2. How ſhould the conſideration of this make us w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> patience bear the Croſs, &amp; run to the Crown, make us w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> care to prepare for Chriſts coming &amp; with an earneſt deſire &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.19. to wiſh and long &amp; look for it, ſtill cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Come, Lord Jeſus, come quickly!</hi> Rev. 22.20. It remaineth now that wee ſpeak of the third obſervable in the text, the Perſons to bee judged,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:121493:28"/>
               <hi>Wee all:</hi> Whence this doctrine,</p>
            <p n="3">III. <hi>The laſt Judgement ſhall bee generall.</hi> It ſhall bee more general then Death. Some have already e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcaped death as Enoch &amp; Elijah: ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſhall eſcape it, even all <hi>that ſhall bee found alive at Chriſts coming,</hi> 1 Cor. 15.51. 1 Theſſ. 4.17. But none ſhall eſcape judgement. <hi>All that are in the graves ſhall hear Chriſts voice,</hi> Joh. 5.28. <hi>All ſhall appear before his judgement-ſeat,</hi> 2 Cor. 5.10. whether Smal or Great, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.12. whether Quick or Dead, <hi>Acts</hi> 10.42. whether Juſt or Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt, <hi>Acts</hi> 24.15. So that the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets <hi>Many,</hi> Dan. 12.2. is to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded by the Apoſtles <hi>All</hi> here; All ſhall awake out of the duſt, for All ſhall ſtand before the tribunall; high &amp; low, rich and poor, one with another, from him that ſitteth on the throne to her that grindeth at the mill. There ſhall bee no acception or
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:121493:29"/>exception of perſons no ſanctuarie or hiding place, no bribe, no appeal, no appearing by Proxy or Atturney, no pleading by Counſel, but every man ſhall ſtand at the barre in his own perſon to give account of himſelf to the Judge. Every mans actions ſhall bee ſcanned, and ſifted &amp; weighed in the balance of the Sanctuarie: Every one ſhal be tried &amp; judged by Gods Law concerning <hi>every thing that hee hath done in his body whether good or bad,</hi> 2 Cor. 5.10. Yea, not onely deeds, but words ſhall bee accounted for, <hi>Matth.</hi> 12.36. yea, thoughts, <hi>Acts</hi> 8.22. <hi>Ro.</hi> 2.16. yea, not onely commiſſions of evil, but omiſſions of good; not onely the waſting of our ſubſtance with the Prodigall, but the not employing of our talent with the ſlothfull ſervant. Thou muſt bee rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned with for all that God hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed on thee, for all the gifts of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, for all the means of grace, for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:121493:29"/>Sabbath thou haſt enjoyed, for every Sermon thou haſt heard, for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very bleſſing received, for every cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection inflicted, for the time that God hath lent thee, &amp; the opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitles of well-doing. Thou ſhalt bee queſtioned how thou haſt uſed the membres of thy body, how thou haſt employed the faculties of thy ſoul, how thou haſt gotten and how thou haſt ſpent thine eſtate, how thou ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſt into and how thou haſt diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged thy calling. Every man ſhall bee ſummoned in particular to give an account of his ſtewardſhip, <hi>Luke</hi> 16.2. An exact and ſtrict ſurvey ſhall bee taken of all that wee have done, ſpoken, thought; of every ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving cogitation idle word, unadviſed action; of every duty omitted, ſinne committed, creature abuſed, means neglected, time misſpent. Here wee take notice but of a few matters a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs in our lives; but at that day the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:121493:30"/>leaſt ſinnes ſhall bee made to appear before all the world. For as in the beams of the Sun the leaſt motes are diſcerned, ſo ſhall the ſmalleſt <hi>pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dillos</hi> bee diſcovered by the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Chriſts coming. And if the leaſt, how much more the greateſt? If <hi>for every idle word that men ſpeak they ſhall give account in the day of judgement,</hi> Matth. 12.36. how much more for Lying, Swearing, Forſwearing, Curſing, Blaſphem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing? If wee muſt bee anſwerable for the utmoſt farthing, how much more for Covetouſneſs Oppreſſion, Glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tony, Drunkenneſs, Theft, Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie, Murder, Rebellion? The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of this ſtrict tribunall ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the godly themſelves oft to tremble and quake. <hi>Quoties diem illum conſidero, toto corde contremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſco,</hi> ſaith Hierome. And if holy men bee afraid, oh what cauſe have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane ones to bee aſtoniſhed! <hi>If the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:121493:30"/>righteous ſearcely bee ſaved, where ſhall the ungodly and ſinner appear?</hi> 1 Pet. 4.18. How will the faces of all wicked wretches bee covered with ſhame, when thoſe abominable ſinnes which they now dig deep to hide from the ey of the world, ſhall all bee made manifeſt to men and angels! If yee ask mee now, as they <hi>Acts</hi> 2.37. What ſhall wee do, that wee may ſtand with comfort before the judgement-ſeat of Chriſt? I anſwer;
<list>
                  <item>I. Let us all judge our ſelves un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partially.</item>
                  <item>II. Let none judge others raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</item>
                  <item>III. Let Magiſtrates judge juſtly.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">I. Such is the Knowledge and Power of the Judge (as yee have heard) that it will bee altogether impoſſible for any man to hide him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf from him. Neither the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:121493:31"/>nor the waves will bee able to cover thee from him that will com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the Sea, the Earth, Death and Hell to give-up their dead, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.13. But though thou canſt not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal thy perſon, yet (which is far better) thou mayeſt conceal thy ſins from the ey of the Judge, by confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and forſaking them now: 1 Joh. 1.9. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32.5. If thou diſcover them now, they will bee covered then. If in the petite Court of thine own Conſcience thou call thy ſelf to accompt, and condemn thy ſelf for thy tranſgreſſions, thou ſhalt bee acquitted at the generall Aſſiſes. Hear the Wiſe mans words: <hi>Prov.</hi> 28, 13. <hi>Hee that hideth his ſins, ſhall not proſper; but hee that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth and forſaketh them, ſhall have mercie.</hi> So S. Peter, <hi>Acts</hi> 3.19. <hi>Repent yee, and bee converted, that your ſins may bee blotted out when the times of refreſhing ſhall
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:121493:31"/>come from the preſence of the Lord.</hi> Every ſin wee committ, God ſetteth it on our ſcore, till wee repent: but penitent tears waſh all out. This Peter having found true by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, <hi>Mark</hi> 14.72. <hi>&amp;</hi> 16.7. commendeth a Remedie with a <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batum eſt.</hi> David, Manaſſeh, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie Magdalene, all Gods Saints, have proved this courſe effectuall. Let us take it. Let us arraign our<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves at the barre of our own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, rip-up our hearts and lives, confeſs our ſins with ſorrow and ſhame, condemn ourſelves for them, repent unfeignedly of them, and turn from them, and then wee ſhall find all blotted out at that day. The Judge will take all on himſelf, will plead for us, and diſcharge us. But if wee <hi>cover our tranſgreſſions, as Adam, by hiding our iniquity in our boſome,</hi> Job 31.33. wee ſhall find that as the buſhes could not
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:121493:32"/>hide him, ſo neither ſhall the hills hide us. For if wee neglect this du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, aſſure wee ourſelves the Judge will not; but if wee forget our ſins, hee will remember them; and if wee caſt them behind our backs, hee will <hi>ſet them in order before our faces,</hi> Pſal. 50.21. Oh let us not put the Judge to this, but let us ſave him the labour of judging by judging ourſelves. His judgement (as yee have heard) is terrible; <hi>It is a fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full thing to fall into the hands of the living God,</hi> Hebr. 10.31. <hi>and who may stand in his ſight when once hee is angry?</hi> Pſal. 76.7. but our judging of ourſelves is proſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table. For though haply <hi>for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent</hi> (as Correction, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12.11.) <hi>it bee not joyous but grievous, yet afterwards it yieldeth the peaceable fruit of righteouſneſs to thoſe that are exerciſed thereby.</hi> For ſo ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>If wee would judge
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:121493:32"/>ourſelves, wee ſhould not bee judged,</hi> that is, <hi>wee ſhould not bee condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the world,</hi> 1 Cor. 11.31, 32, This is one Uſe.</p>
            <p n="2">II. If yee would not bee judged yourſelves, then judge not others. It is our Saviours caveat, <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.1. <hi>Judge not, that yee bee not judged;</hi> yea, and the Apoſtles argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in this very place, <hi>Why doſt thou judge thy brother? or why doſt thou ſet at naught thy brother? for wee ſhall all stand before the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment-ſeat of Christ.</hi> So it ſhould bee read: for there is an illative par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in the Originall, which ſhould not have been left out in the Tranſlation. This <hi>For</hi> uſhereth-in a double argument againſt proud and Phariſaicall judging, againſt buſy and uncharitable cenſuring of other men, one from the perſons to bee judged at the laſt day, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from the Judge: 1. Wee ſhall
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:121493:33"/>all bee judged: therefore leave med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dling with thy brothers affairs, and look well to thy ſelf. 2. Chriſt is the Judge of all: therefore uſurp not his office; ſtep not from the barre to the bench. This would bee preſumption and ſacrilege; the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, folly and uncharitableneſs. S. James argueth after the ſame ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, <hi>Jam.</hi> 4.11, 12. <hi>Speak not evill one of another, brethren: Hee that ſpeaketh evil of his brother, and judgeth his brother, ſpeaketh evil of the law, and judgeth the law: but if thou judge the law, thou art not a doer of the law, but a judge. There is one Lawgiver, who is able to ſave and to deſtroy: who art thou that judgest another?</hi> What abſurd and ſawcy impudence would it bee for priſoners, who are all in the ſame condemnation, to doom and damne one another? Yet how common is this ſin, this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:121493:33"/>this putting an oar into other mens boats? Who is there al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt that is not more curious to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire after others, then carefull to mind his own duty? more ready to ſay as Peter concerning John, <hi>John</hi> 21.21. <hi>What ſhall this man do?</hi> then, as they to him, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.37. <hi>What ſhall I do?</hi> How uſuall a thing is it to hear the Countrey-man blame the Citizen, and the Citizen the Countrey-man, and both the Clergy-man? how ordinarie, even among thoſe that profeſs religion, to find men ſpying motes and ſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing gnats in their brethren, and yet bearing beams and ſwallowing ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mels in themſelves! <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 23.24. And truly for the moſt part ſuch as are ſo quick-ſighted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, are, as the <hi>Lamiae,</hi> blind at home. It is a good obſervation of Plutarch's, that as it is a ſhrewd ſigne that they have a durty and an
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:121493:34"/>ill-ordered houſe of their own, who love to gad much abroad, ſo it is probable that they have foul con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences in their boſomes that love to peep much into other mens mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. This wee gather from <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.3. No ey ſo good at ſpying a mote as that which hath a beam in it. None ſo ready to find fault with the waſt of the ointment as hee that was about to ſell his Maſters bloud, <hi>John</hi> 12.4, 5. Know this, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever thou art that buſieſt thy ſelf with thy brothers accounts and thy Maſters office, that thy condemning of others will not excuſe thy ſelf. I have heard it hath been ſo ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in Courts below, that an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender hath eſcaped by impeaching his fellows: but it will bee ſo far from ſtanding thee in ſtead at the barre above, that it will bee added to the bill of thy ſinnes, and enflame thy rekoning. See what the Apoſtle
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:121493:34"/>ſaith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.1. <hi>Thou art inexcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable, O man, whoſoever thou art that judgest.</hi> Leave prying there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore into other mens actions and paſſing thy ſentence upon them, and turn thine ey inward, and examin thine own conſcience, and I war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant thee thou ſhalt find matter enough at home to find fault with, and buſineſs enough to caſt-up thine own accounts, and no leiſure or liſt at all to caſt ſtones at others, <hi>John</hi> 8.7.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> Doth not our Saviour ſay, <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.16, 20. <hi>By their fruits yee ſhall know them?</hi> therefore jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging his lawfull. Or, if judging bee not lawfull, down with the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> When actions are notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly evil, we may reprove and cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure them, we ought to beware of the perſons that committ them, yea wee may ſafely judge the tree to be yet
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:121493:35"/>evill that is wont to bear ſuch fruit: But to determin the finall condition of ſuch a tree, and to ſay it ſhall bee feuell for hell, is high and dangerous preſumption. For ought thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt God may better the nature of it, and make it a plant of Paradiſe. <hi>Judge nothing</hi> therefore <hi>before the time,</hi> 1 Cor. 4.5. nothing raſhly, nothing harſhly, nothing without ground, nothing againſt charity. Such judging it is that the Scripture forbiddeth.</p>
            <p>But this maketh nothing againſt publick judging, nothing againſt the civile Magiſtrate, whoſe calling is as clearly warranted by Gods Word as the exſecution thereof is profitable to humane ſociety. <hi>By mee Kings reigne, and Princes decree justice: By mee Princes rule and nobles, even all the Judges of the earth,</hi> Pro. 8.15 16. The Judge here in the text would not invade the Judges office, <hi>Luke</hi>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:121493:35"/>12.14. and commandeth that Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar have his due as well as God, <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.21. The Apoſtles agree with their Maſter: S. Paul, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. telleth us that the Magiſtrate <hi>is or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained of God</hi> and that <hi>hee is the Miniſter of God for our good;</hi> &amp; that wee muſt afford him <hi>ſubjection tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute, fear, honour.</hi> S. Peter ſaith the like, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 11.13-17. And S. Jude ſharply inveigheth againſt ſuch as <hi>deſpiſe dominion, &amp; ſpeak evil of dignities,</hi> verſ. 8. Since the Scripture is ſo clear for this point, how into<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerably too blame are they that abuſe this ſpirituall ſword to blunt the edge of the temporall, &amp; ſlander Magiſtracy and civile Juſtice, as if it could not ſtand with Religion &amp; Chriſtianity! Such affronts as theſe that are put upon the Judgement<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeat it ſelf mee thinketh ſhould rouſe up the ſpirit even of a Gallio, and make him, how careleſſe ſoever of
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:121493:36"/>other things, to take care of himſelf and his freehold. God put true zele and courage into the hearts of all Magiſtrates, that they may magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie their office by doing juſtice and judgement. That is the third Uſe of the Text, That</p>
            <p n="3">III. Judges ſhould judge juſtly. Of this but a word; <hi>Verbum ſapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enti.</hi> The Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Wee ſhall all ſtand before the judgement-ſeat of Chriſt:</hi> Let mee a little alter the words, &amp; tell all Judges and Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, That Chriſt ſtandeth before their judgement-ſeats. The Aethio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pians (as Franciſcus Alvarez report<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth) uſed to ſet many chairs about the tribunalls of Judges, imagin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Gods would come and ſit down in them. That which they did but imagin, the Scripture aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth us of, That <hi>the Lord is with Judges in the judgement,</hi> 2 Chron. 19.6. That <hi>God ſtandeth in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:121493:36"/>of the mighty, and jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth among the Gods,</hi> Pſ. 82.1. The Turkiſh Juſticers in the Divan (they ſay) dare at no time tranſgreſs the Law, becauſe ſometimes the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour is wont to ſtand behind the hangings, and they know not when hee is abſent: How much more ſhould Chriſtian Magiſtrates, and all that have to do in Courts of judicature, ſtand in aw, and ſinne not, when they conſider that the Lord is ever amongſt them, and though they ſee him not, yet hee ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth notice of every perſon, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerveth every particular; the ground and menaging, and iſsue of every ſuit; what conſcience the Jury make of their oath; the maner and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives of the Lawyers pleading, and of the Judges giving ſentence! How ſhould this make them all (as Jehoſhaphat enjoyneth, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 19.6.) <hi>take heed what they do;</hi> eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:121493:37"/>the Judge, who beeing Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intendent over the whole affair, is accountable not onely for his own actions, but for whatſoever miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages hee might have hindred, or ſhould have puniſhed, and did not. Let every one therefore that ſitteth on the Bench think of that dreadfull Tribunall in the Text, and let him not ſo much look about him, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him, to conſider his power, as above him, to conſider him that gave him his commiſsion, and to whom hee muſt render an account. In ſome countreyes Judges were pictured without eyes, and Juſtice commonly is ſo: But God grant our Judges and Juſtices may have their eyes in their heads, and fix one on him that ſeeth in ſecret, and the other on the cauſe that is brought before them. And indeed let them but bethink and beſpeak themſelves with Job, <hi>What ſhall wee do when
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:121493:37"/>God riſeth up? and when hee viſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, what ſhall wee anſwer him?</hi> Job 31.14. and they will readily follow Jobs practice, and <hi>not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the poor from their deſire, nor cauſe the eyes of the widow to fail, nor lift up their hand againſt the fatherleſs, though they ſee their help in the gate,</hi> verſ. 16, 21. They will follow the Prophets counſel, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 33.15. They will <hi>walk righteouſly, ſpeak uprightly, deſpiſe the gain of oppreſſions, and ſhake their hands from holding of bribes;</hi> They will neither ſuffer the golden eloquence of Advocates that plead in publick, nor the eloquent gold of ſuch as would bribe in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate, to blind their eyes, and cauſe them to pervert or deny or delay juſtice; They will contemne the favours, and frowns, and threats of men, though never ſo mighty or many; They will not bee charmed
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:121493:38"/>by letters, or ſuits; they will not bee led by paſſion, or prejudice, or par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiality; but they will <hi>hear the ſmall as well as the great,</hi> Deut. 1.17. and puniſh the great as well as the ſmall, and adminiſter juſtice with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reſpect of perſons. Thus righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous will Judges bee in their judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, if they will ſadly and fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently fix their thoughts on the judgement-ſeat of Chriſt. They will <hi>ſerve the Lord with fear, and rejoyce with trembling,</hi> Pſal. 2.11. they will fear to offend him, and bee carefull to pleaſe and imitate him: And ſo doing, (beſides the many poſitive bleſſings that ſhall flow from their judgement-ſeats) they ſhall bee a means to prevent and remove temporall judgements from the places where they live; and when Death ſhall ſummon them hence, they ſhall bee able to ſtand in the judgement at the generall Aſſiſes;
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:121493:38"/>and when unrighteous Judges and mighty ſinners ſhall bee doom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to mighty torments, they ſhall receive <hi>a crown of righteouſneſs, which the Lord the righteous Judge ſhall give them at that day; and not to them onely, but to all them alſo that love his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing,</hi> 2 Tim. 4.8. To whom with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and the holy Ghoſt be all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and glorie now and for ever. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
